I'd like to thank Yasmin.
She worked very, very hard,
she and her whole team,
all year
to prepare this retreat for us.
[Music]
And without her, we couldn't have a program like this.
So the whole team could stand up,
and
all the volunteers,
please stand up. Yes, thank you.
And I'd like to thank everyone from
Latin America. We'll see how it goes.
We're going to be together for eight days,
and I know many of you came from
very far away.
Thank you for coming.
I think it's hard to find the time
to come here. It's hard to
travel and stay here,
and I'm very grateful that you
came
to this program from Thailand. And Yasmin
had a great idea
and said, "We should tell people to
invite their parents
and their children."
[Music]
That way, people can have a family vacation,
and it's a very nice idea.
[Music]
I think that later in life, that's
the time we remember with our
family together.
I'm very grateful that you had
this idea. I'd like the parents to stand
up.
Thank you very much.
[Applause]
[Music]
And the children, where are the children? They're everywhere!
We owe a round of applause to the children
[Applause]
We have understood, so
today's program
and every day
[Music]
I will teach for three and a half hours in the morning. I
used to teach two or three times a day,
and in the afternoon
everyone is sleepy,
so I decided it was better to have one
long class in the morning. They are
fresh, and I am fresh,
so we will have one long class.
The morning is a good time to
meditate,
but I will take a long break
in the morning,
so don't worry
[Music].
We are not used to sitting like this.
This morning you are fresh, but after
three days you will be tired. You are
just resilient.
It is very important. You
cannot have this teaching anywhere else.
This teaching will help you all your
life,
and this teaching will help you after
death.
So it is different from other teachings.
So it is a very important time for
us.
From time to time you will be tired.
Someday there will be a problem in your
hotel room.
Someday you will miss your refrigerator.
In my house,
just relax
and listen.
Open your heart. We have just
returned from a
special program in Shenzhen
for executives. A special executive program.
Twelve of them are here, and I would like
Welcome,
and I'm here to learn profound ideas
to use in the music business and
in your families.
My hope for this program is that it's not
a religious program.
We have people from Mexico,
Ukraine,
Russia,
andGermany.
Each country has its own culture,
its own religion.
People in Mexico get
married in a church,
and people in Ukraine get
married in a Christian church. We
all have our own family culture,
so I think we should respect each
culture.
People in Mexico don't want to get married in
a Buddhist temple;
their mothers aren't going to like it,
and that's okay.
So, my dream for this week is that
I don't want to be a religious video,
and I don't want to be a fanatic. We're just
friends.
We're going to study very, very profound ideas
that will help you your whole life,
and even after you die, they'll still help you.
Teachers come and go;
teachers grow old,
and teachers change.
But we have many teachers here,
and later, I would like you to be
teachers.
It's good to respect a teacher,
but not too much.
Respect the teaching,
and you will be happy.
So, today I'm going to share with you,
and maybe someday you will share
here.  Upstairs,
just relax,
learn these ideas, take them home,
use them quietly
in your different countries, in your
different cultures,
and you will have a happy life.
Usually, we start with a meditation
in the morning
because you are fresh,
and then we will have some teaching.
This is a famous book.
My teacher taught it to me
for 30 years.
We lived together;
we are like an old married couple,
and he was very kind to me.
He taught me this book three times,
very slowly
each time, for about 10 years.
He taught each word slowly
and enjoyed it
like the only good thing at
McDonald's.
[Music]
Meat is not good for you.
They kill 10 million chickens every year.
Don't eat it.
But French fries are very
good,
but don't play fast. Enjoy them.
So, I
started doing this teaching eight years ago.
We are halfway through.
I am spending the teaching like
French fries and enjoying it.
Just enjoy it, have fun. It
is very important
when you come to this kind of teaching.
Go swimming,
eat too much,
sleep a lot—
not in the class,
but have fun.
We are on vacation.  Dharma,
but it's important to relax too, so
have fun
and we're going to have fun together.
So I'm going to teach you a meditation.
The children can go.
The children are for a special class for
children
in Haiti. Welcome from the kit classes. Twitter:
Juanjo Triguero. I would like to
welcome the
special children's class teacher from Canada.
He has many years of experience
[Music]. He
also did a three-year silent retreat
in a small room,
so he is a great teacher.
But he also had a lot of experience
teaching children from China,
so we are lucky that he is
here.
There is a special meditation. I
have taught it for two or three years.
We started it in Mexico. The
group from Mexico could stop. They have
all become teachers.
They finished the 18 courses,
in fact, in classes and institutes, and now they
are teaching them.
So I hope you can learn to
do that.
But we started this meditation in Mexico,
I remember. So
let me tell you the story of
this meditation. I
told you last time. It
comes from Asaga.
He lived 1700 years ago,
and his books are famous in China,
especially The Low Connection.  Llana
and many of his books have been translated,
and he's at the school of the speakers
as well, so I think his books are
famous
[Music]
and very helpful
[Music].
He met Maitreya,
the future Buddha,
and studied with him. He
taught me this
very famous meditation.
This meditation is supposed to be very
good
for understanding your future life,
so we'll work on it. It
has five parts. I
usually do one part at a retreat.
I think you're ready to go
for all five parts.
It takes a little time,
so each day we'll do one more part. Let's do it.
Here we go. Are you ready?
Sometimes when I teach meditation,
some people get on the floor
quickly. Let's meditate.
We have to do this lotus flower pose,
and I say, why?
Or, Buddha always sat like this on the floor,
and I say, but don't you understand why?
2,000 years ago there weren't any chairs.
A chair is fine.
It's fine to meditate in a chair. I
had one, an official
Lion Dance meditation cushion, which are kind of...
but I put it on my sofa.
How's that
more comfortable?
Ah,
so you can sit in a chair, keeping your
feet upright on the floor,
right?  Don't cross your legs when you're in
a chair.
Just sit up straight.
When we meditate in a group, it's
very important to be silent. It
helps the other people. He
said, "
Always turn off your cell phone
before meditating,
and it's good to clear your throat now."
[Music]
And they're finished. Now,
no more on
the hands. You have a choice.
If the room is a little cold for
you,
you can put your left hand down
first
and your right hand on top.
In the pictures, the Buddha is like this,
but if you do it like this, it
really distracts you from your meditation
because you're thinking about your thumbs,
how to keep them.
I like to just relax,
relax my thumbs on top. I
mean, the room was very, very
hot.
Of our options, it
can be like this:
hands down or in the middle.
Then your wrists hurt. I
also did a three-year silent retreat
from 2002-2003.
I stayed in a room, did
n't speak for three years. I
tried everything.
[Music]
Well, and I found the right way. The
right way is the one that's good
for you.
[Music]
Everyone is different. Everyone
has different bodies,
so try a different one
and whatever is comfortable for you.
My body and your body are different, so  For
example,
your doctor
needs to sit differently.
Maybe you're medium-sized, maybe you
're a general.
Everyone's world is different,
so being different,
try different things
and see what's comfortable for you. Activate them.
[Music]
Whatever you choose, it's good to
have your thumb and forefinger together
close, and the parana won't travel
around.
You can try not to touch your fingers.
You can feel the last one moving; it's the
energy moving. Try it.
Here we go. It's
very relaxed.
Sometimes when I meditate, my shoulders
get stiff,
and I have to be careful to loosen
them.
Some meditation teachers
told me that my shoulders are very
stiff.
The mouth is relaxed.
A small smile will help the parana
move.
The stomach should be slightly
tight,
and the forehead should be relaxed.
The eyes are relaxed.
Now, let's learn the Lion Dance.
We're going to learn a part of it today.
[Music]
Normally in meditation, we start
by observing the breath,
but in the Lion Dance, we
then begin with the breath.
We start with some sound from the
room.
So in this room,
we have a small air conditioning noise.
Focus on that sound,
with your mind on the sound.
When we go to sleep in the  At night,
we lay our heads on the pillow.
In the lion dance, you
put your mind on the sound as you lay
your head on the pillow.
Let's try it.
Just listen to the sound.
We're beginning concentration.
Now let's go deeper.
Try to feel your heartbeat.
So, your mind goes to your heartbeat.
Now let's go inside the heart.
The heart is like a small apartment.
Imagine you're inside the heart.
The walls of the heart beat
around you,
and it's not a dark or damp place.
It's in the elegant little apartment.
The sun's rays come in through the
windows.
It feels very beautiful and open.
So let's go inside our hearts
and enjoy more silence.
We're going to meditate for many days,
and the apra (acute respiratory distress) won't increase.
And sometimes it increases too much.
So there's a special way to
help prevent the apra from increasing too
much,
and I'd like you to learn it right now
because we'll be meditating for many
days.
When you breathe in and out,
the breaths will stop at the end
of the breath,
but there's still a little bit of air left inside
the lungs,
and it will accumulate,
and you'll have too much chesty air,
and you'll feel nervous.
So, a special method you can
use
When you exhale,
when your lungs stop
exhaling,
then push out a little more
so that the exhalation is long. Then
there's a pause, and then another
exhalation.
If you're very aware of your
breathing
and do this special method,
then you won't be nervous.
So, let's understand it as five or six
breaths.
When you come out at the
end of the breath,
a little extra exhalation.
The rest is normal.
Let's try it together.
When your lungs stop
exhaling,
exhale a little more.
Now, let's go back to the apartment of
our heart.
Imagine that this apartment is a little
bigger.
I like to imagine it as a penthouse, at the
top of the building. It
has many rooms,
and so I'm going to walk to the middle room
and meditate there.
Many rays of light come in,
but the sound of the
heartbeats in the walls is a
little farther away,
quieter.
Now, in that small meditation room,
there's a small table next to me.
On the table, there's a small jar of
sugar. I
open the lid of the jar,
put my finger in the sugar,
and when I take my finger out, there's
a small grain of sugar on my
finger.
So, I want my meditation...  So I want it to be
deeper and stronger, so I
decide to put my mind inside the
sugar grain.
So my mind gets smaller, smaller, smaller,
and a small window opens in the
sugar grain.
In my mind, I go inside the sugar grain,
very small,
like the tip of a needle.
And when I enter the sugar summer,
I am very surprised.
Inside, it is a very beautiful room,
like a very luxurious apartment, with
many very beautiful cushions,
and the sun's rays are
gently coming in. It's
a perfect meditation room,
and I stay in this quiet place
and enjoy it.
Now I would like to open my mind a little
more
because this little sugar grain can
feel a bit cramped.
So my mind becomes the water
of the Pacific Ocean
and expands to the shores of this world.
Some are touching Thailand,
some leaves are filling up, some
are touching California.
Very, very, very big,
very wide, very
quiet,
very deep.
So imagine your mind
still inside the sugar grain,
but as big as the Pacific Ocean,
and calm
and quiet. And deep down,
now I would like my mind to be bigger.
Expand my mind to the sky
above the ocean.
So my mind expands to the whole
sky, the ocean,
and the other half  It expands into the whole
blue of the sky,
very big,
very open, very
quiet,
very relaxed.
Now take three deep breaths.
Don't forget to push the air out a little more
after each exhale,
and slowly open your eyes. I
like to stretch, see,
and it's very good to have something to drink. I'm
going to need some microphones for
questions.
It's important to stay warm. In
class,
we have people from many different
countries.
Some like the cold, some
like the heat.
[Music]
So we'll make the room a little
cool.
Please bring a shawl
because the air conditioning can make us
sick,
so please bring shawls.
We're going to take a break of about 10
minutes
for a bathroom break,
but if you have any questions
about your meditation, it
can be about this meditation
or any meditation you're
doing.
If you want to ask something, please
raise your hand,
and we'll have microphones.
[Music]
I'd like to know the benefits of doing
this meditation.
Well,
this meditation has two parts,
nine steps.
We'll go through the nine steps.
What's number one?
The air conditioning. We count that as
level zero.
It's true, the air conditioning is
first,
but it's not meditation. We're just
listening to the air conditioning.
After the air conditioning,
the heart.
That's the  First,
first step, then what?
And inside the heart,
that's step two. What's the third?
Further inside, to the center of the heart, it
seems like the fourth
grain of sugar.
Fifth,
or rather,
sixth
heaven.
And if 16 parts,
two more to complete the eight parts.
The benefits of these eight parts are
not to make the mind quieter. There's
no important content.
These aren't important meditations.
The purpose of these first eight
levels
is strong; they're
just exercising the mind,
like ping-pong players.
First, they stretch and prepare, but it's not
the game; it's just a warm-up.
The first eight steps are
n't the game; they're
just warming up, warming up for the
mind, down to the
smallest level, to the
deepest level of the heart.
Warming up, exercising the mind. It
really can make your head spin, but
maybe your hair will fall out—
a little dangerous.
Then step nine is the
important content.
Level nine, we'll
go to the past life; we'll go
to your master.
These are great benefits,
to stop death
for many people.
[Music]
Seeing our past lives, seeing our
future lives
is very important in this world.
Everyone is excited about this life:
how can I make money? Can I get a
girlfriend?
We're interested in this life.
[Music]
But it's good to understand what's going to happen
after I usually see it. It's
good to understand where it comes from.
Value our past life.
The purpose of coming to Thailand
in a normal life. We do
n't think much about our past lives. We
think about our future lives, and that's okay. We have
responsibilities. We have to take
care of our children,
our parents. It's
good to focus on this life,
but it's also good for bread, art,
for the future.
F1, your heart to live for Thailand.
If you know you're going on a trip in three
days, it would be good to start packing your
suitcase from today.
Some of us didn't do that.
My plane was leaving at nine at night
from Shenzhen.
At 8, I was packing
too rushed, too late. I
also left my coffee.
[Music]
So it's better
if you already know you're going on a
trip
to the next life.
It's better to prepare from now on, pack your
suitcase three days before,
and then you can relax and you won't
forget anything.
[Music]
That's the purpose of coming to Thailand.
In your normal life, your
normal job,
focus on
family, work,
parents.
Focus
when you go to Thailand.
Pack your suitcase,
the more lethal this is,
this is the time to take care of your
next life,
so that's the biggest benefit
of level 9.
We're going to prepare for our photographer life
and we're going to try to see emptiness
again.
If you see it correctly,
you can throw away the suitcase. There is
no afterlife.
You become a Buddha,
and that can happen to anyone.
That's the purpose of level 9. The
first 8 are
just warm-ups.
If your flight is a
ping pong competition like the Olympics,
then it's so literary that it's a
ping pong competition at 9
pm.
Stanley is in his hotel
getting ready. He
forgot to come and play ping pong.
Everyone wonders where this
law of the competition is, and he
keeps warming up. Where?
In the hotel room? Fool, talk whatever comes.
You understand,
level 9 is the game. The first 8
levels are warm-ups.
Don't stop at the warm-up.
That's not the ping pong game, it's just
preparation.
Some people say, "Oh, I'm going to watch
my breathing, I'm going to listen to the air
conditioner, or listen to my heart for
an hour."  Two hours
and it's over.
They understand, only the
warm-up counts, but they're not going to the games.
Let's take a 15-minute break. There will be
a bell.
Have a good rest.
Relax. Okay, good start. Let's begin.
Let's begin by opening the paths in
the step.
[Music]
This is a very famous book.
The name of the book
is the name of the soft action. It means
freedom, freedom from death, freedom from aging, freedom
from suffering,
freedom for everyone.
[Music]
And the "cha"
means if this is freedom. And I
say, Stanley, show me your hand,
and then he takes it. Take it. It's like this. It
means that the master
has liberation. He
pays me and says, "Give me your hand," and that's it, take
it.
That's the name of this book.
So if you study, you're going to
have this
liberation,
and you can give it to other people.
So during these 78 days, you'll have
two jobs.
Number 1:
Accept the level and take it, keep it,
but also learn to give it to other
people.
So you have a special notebook.
I put a lot of extra space in it.
You can take notes
because when you share with others, you
need to have good notes.
Don't be like that famous person who
went to the  Class
for 8 days
and then went home.
People ask you what you learned. I said
a nine-step lion dance meditation.
And then your friends say, "Nothing,
really. What's the first one?" "The
first one, I do
n't remember." "What's the second one?" "
The second one." "What's so important?" "
What's the third one?" "
Probably the ocean."
[Music]
It's number 5. So take notes.
When someone asks you a question,
you can help them
too. We're going to have a special recap. I've been
teaching this book, La Riva,
for eight years,
and we'll have a special recap.
So every day I
can help you review,
and we have special groups, right, in
time for review.
[Music]
But I'm going to review a little bit now with
you.
When will it be...  You go home
and people ask you what you studied
and you say a nine-step validation. They
ask you what the nine
steps are.
Let me check my
notes to tell you how good I am. I
have good notes,
but we were asked to take good notes.
You can teach your friends
personally.
Take notes.
Go to the cafeteria
and share with your friends.
[Music]
Two things happen when you share with
your friends:
all the Buddhas in the universe come to
watch.
[Music]
If you're sharing with your friends, it's
very crowded.
Too many Buddhas are watching you
and are happy,
like your mother or father.
Or look, she went to the cafeteria with her friends.
Let's go listen.
Or she's teaching them the nine levels.
Very good.
We're happy.
[Music]
Every time a person
shares with other people, the
Buddhas will come to observe.
So don't embarrass me.
Don't teach them that level 3 is level 5.
The Buddhas will go to that framework. I teach them
those levels incorrectly.
Once you share with another person
personally, it
attracts Buddhas
like honey attracts bees.
Really, it's not a story. It
has power.
[Music]
They have good  I have a nose for when someone is
teaching
or seriously doing the nine steps correctly.
Very good.
Second thing, at
that moment
you are a lama, you are a master. You
become a master. You
are no less a master than management.
Likewise, if you share correctly
in the cafeteria, you are a true master.
Don't think I am a true master, you
are a true master.
And both are very happy
and are there,
so don't doubt it. Two things:
if you share correctly from your notes,
number 1,
the Judases are going to come.
Check it out,
did it very well.
At that moment
you are a true master, like Buddha,
like a lama,
because the nine steps are true teachings, it
is the true teaching.
So please take good notes.
Let's go to where we are going after eight
years.
This is a special book
called Steps on the Path.
[Music]
Say it, the rhyme. I mean,
step by step. You do
n't have to be a special person, you do
n't have to be a monk. You
can be in a family,
a good job, you
should,
and then in your life, in
your family life,
in your work.
For example, I spent 19 years in the
diamond business
while studying my milk course
during the day, and  Well, my job made
money, I
helped my family, I
helped charity,
and then I studied
in the evenings and
on weekends. It
should be a responsible life.
We have jobs,
you can have a nice house, a nice
car, a nice
family. Take responsibility
and study, man.
So we're studying hunger.
You can do both, you should do
both.
[Music]
The person who doesn't take responsibility
for their job and their family won't
take good responsibility for the
gun either.
[Music]
And you should be successful.
The gun is supposed to make you
smarter, it's
supposed to make your mind
brighter. You should
be successful, you should
have a good family,
your kids should play the drums. Just
kidding.
We've arrived at this special place in
hunger.
They're talking about the problems of this
life. It
means you should pack your suitcase
for the next life.
Take care of your next life
because you're going to die.
Everyone thinks they're not going to die.
Their great-grandmother died.
Yes,
your grandmother died. Yes,
your mother died. My mother died. You died.
And so we think. Great-grandmother is gone.
My grandmother is dead.
My mother is dead.
Now it's my turn. Don't you think you're
different? We are.
In this book it says
that a day will come
when  The youngest person in this
room will
also die,
then there will be no one left.
The person who wrote this book
said that during this time. I wrote the book
and it became true. Now everyone is gone.
The person who wrote this book is the
teacher of my teacher,
and my teacher is gone too. The book,
the book writer, died. His
student is gone too.
[Music]
His students, that's me.
So it comes.
You can be sad
and I don't want to think about it.
If your child does something wrong,
you're going to put a blanket over their
head.
Then they think
that since they can't see their mother, their
mother can't see them.
[Music] We
shouldn't be like that. Let's
talk about death
at home,
at your job.
Don't talk about death too much. Be
ready.
In Thailand,
you can talk about it all day
because we want to stop it.
They say you can't shoot the
enemy if you don't know the enemy.
The enemy is death.
We want to kill the enemy.
People ask the man
what his occupation is,
and he says, "On that scale, where's the band?"
I am the killer of death.
Death fears me. I'm
going to kill death.
Is this this job?
That's what we're learning,
to learn about.  Death
is good to study, hunger,
so don't feel depressed,
we're just identifying the
enemy
and then we shoot it.
[Music]
When you have to say
the six times of life, we're going to
study
the animal tubes, and you know the
animals, it's
a type of life
after humans.
[Music]
Then beings of hell.
Everyone says that superstition does
n't exist, hell,
and I'll tell you something interesting.
Obviously, Buddha taught about
hell.
If you do bad karma,
after how you are, you go to hell.
And when I was in school
studying
when I was 17,
the teacher gave us a special course that
lasted about three months.
It's about a
very famous Italian writer named Dante,
and he wrote a book called The Divine
Comedy.
As "medieval" means something funny,
divine, of the gods. It has
three parts.
One part was all about
hell. It
took us a month to finish it,
every detail about hell,
and it's exactly what Agatha taught.
And he was never in China,
but I
saw hell too.
Don't tell me it's a Chinese superstition.
You can read the same thing in the classic European book.
Some people say it's the
best book written in Europe.
Exactly the same,
so if it exists
after you die,
you can become an animal.
If you're lucky, you become a human,
but you can go to hell.
Fourth option:
animal.
And then there are two kinds of superheroes
[Music]
like Iron Man, Spiderman. We
call them little
superheroes, big superheroes.
One is named Dada, one is Agro
Sister.
We say that these people really
exist.
Basic six options.
And of course, we want to come back as a human.
Especially, we don't want to go to hell. We do
n't want to be an animal.
And there are hungry spirits. We do
n't want to be a spirit.
At least we want to be human. It would
n't be a special thing.
If you understand
this very well, you
have a guarantee. You can't
go down. Impossible. After you
die, it's
like a wedding contract.
If you really understand
the emptiness after you die, you can't
say down. You can't come back as an
animal. You can't go to hell. You can't
be a dying spirit. It's
not possible.
It's like a guarantee.
And the best way to teach it
is with a pen. You've
heard me teach this
many times.
There was a famous time I went to Singapore. I
go to Singapore every year. I
think it's been 10 years, 9 years.
We need  2
[Music]
Every year I teach the feather
at the beginning of the first day,
and after I went eight years, I
only taught the feather for 5 minutes.
After the talk,
a gentleman approached me. He's
not from Singapore, he
's from Europe,
but he said, "Jason Michaels, I
think you're getting a little old." Why do you
say that?
You repeat it. That's all I
repeat.
This feather thing, you teach it every time.
Eight times you taught me, he says, "Did you forget?"
And I said, "No, I didn't forget. I taught you
the feather,
but you didn't use it." Okay,
then I have to teach it again.
Why?
Because if you really understand what
I taught in the next 10 minutes, you can't
go to hell, you can't
turn into an animal, you ca
n't turn into a hungry spirit.
It's important.
When you get home,
you sit next to a really handsome guy
like Stanley.
You can make him smile
and you say, "Where are you from?" "I
'm not from Ginseng." And you say, "Where are you going?" "
Or Thailand?" Because I
already told you about the feather.
No.
So share it with other people. Because
if you share well  You ca
n't deny hell
and that's very good.
You help other people.
If they ask you, do you want water or a game? I
already told you about the pen.
Always have a pen in your pocket,
okay?
[Music]
We have a special university in
America,
the first one we've done. The
second one will be in Singapore.
[Applause]
We teach how to teach the pen.
There are 18 parts to teaching the pen. Let's
see if you can find what's
here. Come on, you
can sleep in the afternoon class. I don't
care, I'm not going to teach it.
But right now it's morning, focus.
You can help someone for many lifetimes.
[Music]
So learn how to teach it.
In two things, when you're teaching, it
should be correct.
Number two, it should be fun.
[Music] I
have an essential friend. He's always
angry.
Don't be so serious.
Life is very short.
Our parents can tell us, "
10 minutes ago they were 20 years old,"
and suddenly, "Oh, what's happening? I'm 65 now." What will happen?
Life is very fast.
And of course, we have many problems in
life.
Every body in this room has
special problems.
We can have a problem contest. Oh, I ca
n't smile because
I have big ones.  Problems
I want is to have a contest of big
problems. Someone here has cancer.
Someone's mom just died
two days ago.
I have to call him after this class.
So, we
all have problems.
We can be people who have
problems and can't smile, or we can
be people who have
problems and can smile.
And the second one is better.
You have problems? Yes,
seriously,
very seriously. And why are you smiling? I do
n't know. It's better if I don't smile.
[Music]
Just smile.
Everyone has problems.
When you show the pen,
very seriously.
[Music]
Or smile. Okay, ready. You
show the pen, but ask your
friends to answer.
Ask a series of questions and
you answer.
I think it's important to tell
people,
just give a natural answer. You
think about it too much. It's
not a philosophy class; it's a
pen class.
Also, a good answer.
What is this thing?
A pen.
A puppy just came in
and showed the pen to the dog.
So, what is he going to do with the pen? Is he
going to bite it?
Does the dog see a pen as a
toy?
Who is right, the dog or the human?
Both?
Because the dog can bite and enjoy it. It's
okay.
And then there's the human.
The dead. My pen.
And the dog says you're a very silly human.
This knows very well why you write.
Don't write with my toy.
Don't bite my pen. One more time with the
toy. It's the same. Okay.
Now, big questions. Questions.
If I put the pen on this table
and all the people leave the room,
all the dogs leave the room, there is
nobody in the room at this
moment, is it
a pen or is it a chew toy? Nothing. It's
nothing.
[Music]
You want to understand emptiness?
This is a piety.
At that moment, what is it? Is it a
chew toy?
A pen?
Nothing.
That's more. Careful.
There are three famous ideas about
emptiness. I'll
teach you number 1.
What is the city?
Everything is black.
That's the city. Okay,
that's fine. No, that doesn't help you. Black, black,
black. It doesn't help you.
You understand this
and you won't be successful in your life. You wo
n't have a good family. You wo
n't be healthy. At 65
[Music]
you'll be like this. It's
just emptiness. It's
not black.
Second,
see the mind.
A thought comes from the left to
the right.
Don't think about it,
just let them pass.
That's not emptiness.
Many people say no.  Think about nothing,
what's the charge of not thinking about anything?
[Music] I'll
show you on my phone, it's
not so... have you seen my phone? You had it
in moments, understand?
That's the karma of trying not to think about
anything,
always losing these phones.
That's what piety is.
Here's the third most famous one,
someone kisses you,
someone hits you, there's
no happiness, no sadness,
nothing.
It's a silly idea. Have
you seen the picture of the Buddha? They're
not so serious,
they were smiling, happy,
with a big smile.
So that's not emptiness, which is low.
When the dog leaves the room and
people leave the room,
then it's
not a feather, it's not a toy, it's silver.
Now
when the person comes back into the
room, that's when I
say hello. This law,
and they turn to look at this thing
and it changes.
What happens? It becomes... what does it become? A
joke. At that moment,
see
more carefully, more carefully. The truth is,
and the feather changes.
Before, it was frosty,
now it's a plate.
When
massive and empty, the feather becomes in the
mouth, like,
then it becomes a joke. It must
come from me,
why?
[Music]
If the dog comes in,
the same thing becomes a toy
for...  Biting then must be coming
from me the first
the feather comes from the human
the toy comes the dog
comes from the feather to me
yes or no
which is the test
[Music]
if the feather comes from the feather then
the dog should write a poem to
his girlfriend
what a pretty tail you have
[Music]
so the feather must be coming from
me
a famous mistake
some people say
ok was teaching
positive thinking
always be positive
everything comes from you
so if you want a diamond
like the secret the law of attraction I do
n't want a feather
I want a diamond so since
everything comes from me diamond diamond
diamond you can
also make a fuss you can
ask I want ahead wants to
take you it comes from me it comes from me
with the first better
or it's still the feather because it
comes from you but there's something
forcing you to see it wrong you
have no choice
what forces you to have a blog
if you have a seed in your mind
seed of the feather
when you enter the room
the seed will open
a small image opens an image of
feathers comes out
65 per second it's so fast but you
can see it
when you meditate a lot
you can see the seeds open
you can see the images come out how many
65  per second
when you watch the video online
if you're in the sweet tournament of language
the internet isn't very good
it cuts out means the image goes
slower it's
supposed to be 24 images per
second
but if the internet isn't very good
the same with your mind
if you meditate a lot
you can see the seeds opening
and coming out of your mind 65 x seconds
[Music]
and the internet 24 per second in
real life 65 per second because
yes you
need extra seeds for smell,
touch, taste
your life is like a video
the seeds are opening 65 per
second
I would like to die of seeds
it's called dependent origination
everything depends on your seeds
origination means the feather starting
this is true
independent origination the seed is coming out
so what is emptiness it's here it's
the place where the mind puts the
seed
[Music]
yes
if the feather is a feather then there is no
space in the feather to be a toy
to bite
the feather is empty then there is
space for the dog's seed to
see a toy and the human's seed to
see a feather
so listen
[Music]
if you learn and know how to plant  One
seed,
you can have anything you want.
Why?
Because your whole life was made of seeds.
Everything comes from seeds.
My teacher taught me for 20 years,
and then he came with me. He
taught you, 'Careful, he
teaches you seeds,
how many things come from seeds,
and all that.'
Then you're ready to play the final exam. He
loves the final exam.
Look at New York City.
I start a business, use the seeds,
and see if you make money. If you do, you
pass the exam. You didn't
learn anything about seeds.
[Music]
Strange exam.
So I did it. As you know, as you know,
we made the
biggest diamond company in the world. We
started with three diamonds.
What are
[Music]
those diamonds? They're smaller than
sugar grade.
Then
we were making 300,000 diamonds
every day.
And I had no
business experience. Number two: I don't like
business. No sprint
making the world live. Without experience, and I do
n't like business. But this was
my final exam,
and
so, if the pen comes from the seed,
then money also comes from the
seed.
Wife, husband, also comes from the
Your body,
a 65-year-old body, also
comes from seeds.
So you can change it.
This is the meaning of emptiness,
so I'll give you four options: one,
the city is a black color;
option number two,
to see, take care not to think about anything,
have a blank mind; number three,
emptiness is
without emotions, don't be sad about our
solidity.
[Music]
That's emptiness.
Jobs in 14,
the largest diamond company in
the world.
A 65-year-old's body is a
25-year-old's body because it comes from you. Do you understand?
Just understand how to plant
a seed. Okay,
what's the next step?
We have to learn how to plant a
seed.
Two worlds,
many volunteers.
[Music] I
have 100 dollars,
forget it. I
want to make a thousand dollars over Brouwer governments.
Those who asked don't have it, those who do
n't ask are the ones who have it.
So seriously,
I want to plant a seed
for 1000 dollars right now.
This isn't the demonstration.
This is how genius Michael makes his
salary. It's
real, really.
I'm planting a seed.
People say it because you do it every
day.
Because I want money, I have to
do it. I have no choice. I have
100 dollars.
I want to teach you.  How to plant
there are four steps
[Music]
and you can say that she teaches this until
last year I do
n't care
[Music] I do
n't want them to go to hell
I want them to go up
if they understand the pen if they
understand the 100 dollars
you are protected
if you have a car accident on a boat
and if you never get home you are protected they do
n't understand I have to do it
and I'm going to keep doing it for the rest
of my life
four steps
to plant a seed
you can make a video
it's fine but
don't put it in a widget it's not
legal it's not appropriate I don't
care
but there is a policy
so please protect everyone and that's it you
can make a video it's a currency
these
[Music]
what here we go I
think this lady
hello hi what's your name
ml
nice I managed so
ml would
help me plant a seed
thank you so I
'm happy she's going to help me
plant a seed
planting seeds has four steps
don't forget
if you learn
you can easily make a great business
you can live to 65
you can have a good family
learn the four steps
use the four steps step number one
you have to decide what you want
Today in my example
I want to make a thousand dollars. My goal
today is to
make a thousand dollars. That's
step number one.
Maybe your step number one is a
much higher goal.
What is a higher goal?
I want my husband to do the dishes
every night. That's a
high goal.
Or maybe I want to be healthy. I do
n't want a beautiful face, I
want a peaceful mind. I
want the whole world to be happy.
You decide. You
can plant any seed,
but today for the demonstration
we're going to plant a thousand dollars for just
two.
You must have a partner to plant your
seed. It's
not possible to plant a seed
if you don't use it with the other person.
I'm very shy. I don't want to talk to
other people. Okay, then forget it. You can
do all four steps, maybe,
but I'm poor,
so you have to be a little strong
and work with the other person,
and you'll help me make a thousand dollars.
So, okay, just do it. Step
number two:
You need a partner.
Step number three:
You must plant a seed.
How to plant a seed? Please
raise your hand. Like this: I
take 100 dollars and put them in
my hand.  No,
and I close his hand
then with it he bit
it
[Music]
finished already plants a seed
how
this is karma
you have to understand how to sow karma
[Music]
and you can
no matter this time under rise
how to sow a seed
you have to see yourself doing
something good
you have to hear yourself
saying something good
so listen I'm going to learn a
seed
[Music]
this sound comes back to my own ear
and makes an impression
after two hours
that impression
turns into charcoal and it's going to open
and make a joke
or it's going to open and make a thousand dollars
when I put them in your hand
and open my hands
that image comes to my eye
and touches my mind it
's a seed in my mind
and the seed is planted
thank you very much
step number 4
if you don't know step number 4
the seed will be separated
but it won't open in 100 years
she's going to have a thousand dollars
and too late we do
n't want to wait 100 years
you have to put water on the seed
you must put water on the seed
like I do on the seeds
it's a special meditation
don't  You're going to do it
with the lotus flower and meditation pose.
When my teacher taught me, he
had a car accident before I
met him,
and I have a sore throat.
But then he spoke like, "Star Wars, he
spoke like this." It's
time for step number four.
And I would say, "What is the name of step
number four? Coffee meditation." And how do you do it? "Do
n't do it like that."
But I'll kill her. You taught me to accept things
sometimes.
Don't do it.
So what do you want?
A special model? I'm
going to teach you the module
[Music]
and others
to the world, special for coffee meditation. Go like this. Yes,
the blows even to your neighbor.
This is moderate.
When we do coffee meditation before
going to sleep,
before sleeping, because
your mind is going to cook all night
while you sleep. It
becomes $1,000 while you sleep,
and your mind cooks while you sleep.
So you should think about the good thing
you did today.
When we sleep,
we like to think about problems.
Why
[Music]?
Because there are so many people in this
room
[Music].
My problem is more serious than yours. I
know you can smile
[Music],
but you don't have my problem. My
problem is very serious.
When I go to sleep, it's
time.  Special
to think again and again and again
and again about my special problem.
My husband isn't happy.
My children aren't going to school, they aren't
studying.
My boss doesn't love me, he
likes the other person
all night. We
're planting bad seeds. Don't
do that.
Don't worry before you go to sleep.
The best time to worry
[Music]
is temporarily in the bathtub
after the sun comes up.
The sunlight has a special power
to make big problems smaller.
The darkness
before you go to sleep, you
're tired.
It's a bad time to think about your
problems.
And now I can think about my problems,
although I give you permission. What time should I think about my problems?
Now should I do my problem
meditation
until morning because they get
smaller. Never do it at
night. At night,
think about me.
Think about her face.
So today everything is going to sleep.
Or I don't remember.
The weak face,
big smile.
She's going to take her friends out to dinner
today. A
really nice dinner, okay,
a special dinner.
And she's like this. She looks so happy.
Before you go to sleep,
think about the good thing you did that
day. Like this, okay, I know
good.
Now, what? I didn't do
anything good. Well,
what did you do yesterday?
Okay, I didn't do
anything yesterday.
And well, 10 years ago,
was this something good?
Oh yes, yes, yes, yes, I did it. I made them look for it,
and they think that's good.
The seed is there.
If you think about the good thing you did,
something good for
someone else, the seed will grow faster because thinking about and being happy about that seed is like watering the seed. Any good thing you did 10 years ago, since 10 years ago was worse than it should have been, you saw someone else do something good.
Yes,
Jazz, well, and his team
work so hard
in Thailand. Incredible, incredible. Okay, so be
happy about that. I'm
going to teach you a special secret. You
know, his team and his
venerable team, chic men,
made a paradise for those who, for the
genes of the people in Thailand,
made very good, great seeds.
They worked for a year
to have everything ready for us. I
have several pieces of news.
[Music]
If you do coffee meditation of their
good seeds, you get 10%.
[Music]
It's a good deal,
a good karma deal.
Okay,
don't worry.
[Music]
They don't lose that 10%.  It gets
bigger than 10%,
so just do it
if you can't remember anything good you did
today.
Then think of something someone else
did that was good, and you have 10%.
I think today,
10% of Yasmin's and her team's karma
is much more than my karma.
[Music]
Open, I
'm not sure.
Teaching is a big coal.
[Music]
Preparing Thailand for the retreat for
500 people is also a big
karma.
Which one should I do? My mind
makes the coffee
about the two. No problems,
okay, Asextra.
Okay,
you can do it if
you understand what I just said
today
about the feather and the seeds.
[Music]
I can guarantee you won't go to
hell
because I can tell you almost
what I'm going to go deeper because
you came to Thailand.
When you think about the seed that makes the
feather,
[Music] you
almost have a guarantee.
If you die today,
which is possible, right? You're
not going down,
person,
because you say almost.
There's one more kind of emptiness you have to
understand to protect yourself. It's
the  The last 5% of emptiness,
but you have to understand it,
so I'm going to teach it to you right now. Don't
forget it
when you teach emptiness at Starbucks
and all the doubters are watching you.
Don't forget the last 5%.
This is the one that really helps the
other person. Here's a real example:
this morning we were teaching the
Lion Dance meditation,
and you said, "Close your eyes,"
and you told us, "Listen to the air
conditioner," and then, "Listen to your
heartbeat."
Yes,
and sorry. During the meditation, just one
thought came to me.
Donate an area that at night
I asked my mind to meditate. It
really doesn't listen
to me. I tell my mind, "
Now let's meditate,"
and the mind says, "Okay."
And I talk to the mind. It said, "
Listen to the air
conditioner." It told it, "Let's
listen to the heartbeat." Can you
do that?
You're talking to your mind. Where is it? Your
mind says, "Yes, let's do it.
Let's do it." What
silence is,
think about the heartbeat. Okay,
and it's really talking to you. Okay,
are you ready? What we're going to start with is
donating the donut.
Donor has donated. Donor
street. Let's go  Concentrate, donut,
dollar, you
don't think about donuts all day,
but when meditation begins, two
sides, side by side, nothing.
Why do you
have a seed in your mind to
think about donuts?
You're not the one speaking inside your
own mind,
you're the one listening. You
always tell your husband, "
Nothing,
darlings, you ca
n't speak and listen at the same
time."
Maybe he tries to be quiet for a minute
so he can tell you something. You ca
n't speak and listen at the same
time,
and it's true.
Inside your own mind, are you the one
speaking
or the one listening
while your wife speaks? You can't
be both.
If your husband speaks
or listens
inside your mind, you
're listening, you ca
n't be speaking.
So who's speaking in my mind?
Who's speaking in my mind?
Seeds.
The seeds are the ones speaking,
not you. There's no
tube speaking inside your
mind.
[Music]
Your mind is empty of you speaking.
I want to listen, listen,
listen. Protect
yourself
after you die. Easy, ask
yourself,
who's speaking in my mind?
The seeds. The seeds are speaking.
There's someone speaking in your mind who isn't
the seed.
I'm protecting from hell now.
There's someone talking inside your mind
that isn't a seed.
That's the emptiness that will protect you.
There's a feather in my hand.
Okay,
some are awake. There's a test in
the summer.
Yes, there's
a test in my hand that comes from
my seeds.
[Music]
Yes,
if I want more, the more, like I put the
feather seed in my mind.
I give a feather and I get happy. That puts
a feather seed in my mind.
There's a feather in my hands. Yes, that's when the
child screams. It
comes from me.
Maybe I have to be nicer.
There's a feather in my hand.
Yes,
there's a feather in my hand that comes from my
seed.
Yes, now, big question. There's a feather in my hand
that doesn't come from
my seed.
[Music]
No, that's the city.
This protects you from going to hell. But
we need a little more.
Are you ready?
Can you hear some thoughts in
your mind in these minutes?
Yes,
you can hear thoughts in your mind
that are coming from seeds.
Yes,
all thoughts come from
seeds.
When you listen to your own mind, you
're listening to seeds opening up in
your mind.
Get a question.
[Music]
There's someone talking in  Your mind not
coming from your own seeds is not
impossible, that's it, it
will take care of you.
If you understand that well, you are protected
forever.
[Music]
I ca
n't be hell, impossible, okay, we're done
now.
[Applause] We
can go to the river now.
[Music]
Just 20 minutes. I know you're tired, I know you
traveled,
and I'm so happy you're here. I
think you're all really cool.
So, 20 more minutes
later, we'll have a break. I
'm looking forward to the break too.
Let's focus for 20 minutes. We'll
go to the book.
My teacher taught me this book word
by word,
and I want to do it that way for
you too. We're going to do word by
word
slowly.
Enjoy the fries.
If you try to get through the fries as
fast as you can, you're going to get a stomachache.
This is really the plan to get through the
fries, so eat slowly and
enjoy.
Enjoy.
Don't try to eat so fast. Are you
ready? Word by word.
That's a tie,
and it sounds really good.
After I die,
because it's human,
if there's a superhero revival, I
think I want to try. I
could be a small superhero like
Spider-Man or
a big superhero
like Iron Man.
They say  In Hollywood,
where they make all the American movies,
if you want to make 100 million dollars,
make a superhero movie.
Always make a superhero movie. It's
not a sensitive movie; it does
n't make money.
If you really want money, it's
a superhero movie. Why do
people love them? I love them too. I don't
go to the movies much,
but I always go to see
superhero movies because
they're so cool.
The name is cool.
When I was a kid, we had Spider-Man,
and I loved it. I read all the
books every day, and I asked my
mom, "
Can I be Spider-Man, Mom?
When I grow up, can I be Spider-Man?" And
she said yes.
And I asked her, "What's the name?" He
became Spider-Man, and she
told me, "A special spider bit me. It's a
radioactive spider." And I said something like, "
Mom!"
And every time I saw a spider, I'd say, "Bite me! Bite me!"
We got a lot of spider bites, but nothing happened, just a
lot of scratching. We
all love superheroes,
and they really exist. That's why
we like the movies because we've
been in their place in the past.
[Music]
The reason you like these
movies
is that  You remember in your past life
that it used to be like this
[Music]
now you're just human so it's
possible
you'll think in your mind
today it's very good
if I die
I'd like to go to that superhero place
[Music]
how powerful are they
much more powerful than Iron Man.
You know what they do for fun
when they were kids? You guys played
marbles in China. We did it
when I was 6 or 7.
The school had to confiscate the
marbles
because we were wasting too much
time. We
call those superheroes the B-mooners.
They like marbles too,
but the marbles are whole planets.
And we broke a whole planet. They're
super powerful,
so it's possible
some people will think,
or I'd like to try
playing marbles with planets again. That's very
cool.
Now the problem is
they have special problems in their world.
We call it the world of others. It
can be there. If you
give a lot of money to ML,
if you give a lot of money, just kidding.
If you do the Lion Dance meditation,
the first eight parts are just the
warm-up over and over again
without going to the  Part number 9
now it just looked special to do
a deba
sounds good no
but there's a problem
[Music]
he comes in the book
teaches the problem of his planets where
they play marbles with the planets a
special problem
apart from the special problem of the others
[Music]
so maybe I decide if I don't want to be
reborn there
[Music] I
prefer to be a Buddha
Buddhas help more people
now who in the book
talks about the special problems
of those debas
[Music]
so I'm going to tell you
and you don't know the language
but it's a very powerful seed in your
mind
it's obvious
so don't worry I hope it's
boring that you use this
ancient language
ooh
[Music]
I'm trying to put a seed in your
mind
here we go
[Music]
so many people have a shawl
if you don't have a shawl maybe you should mine for
gold you
should be in bringing one so you don't get
cold
[Music]
and there are many qualities of a shawl
I was in Ukraine
who was there with me my skull friends
was at the Premier Palace Hotel
I went to buy a  A shawl for my friends, my
old ladies, I don't
know if you know, it's
very expensive, very expensive, a very expensive store, I didn't know, I
just went in
and then, well, we chatted, it's
very good for my
great friend, she's 94 years old,
yesterday we bought her some things, right?
I like to buy her things,
pretty things, pink ones, a red pajama set. I bought her something, I
bought her something at the Premier
Palacio Hotel. I told her I wanted to be there, she
said, "What?"
coins or dollars,
and I was surprised,
300 dollars?
Maybe I don't like that color that much
because we talked about it.
Listen
[Music]
if you wear a 300 dollar shawl for
a day
you're using a lot of seeds, they're
expensive seeds,
these are 300 seeds in a day.
You buy the cheap ones, 100 dollars, it
's not as comfortable
but it's a cheaper seed,
just use the 100 dollar seeds.
[Music] I
'm not telling you to buy cheap clothes, I
'm not telling you that, I
think you should buy pretty clothes
[Music]
and buy for other people,
then you'll always have enough
seeds to wear the pretty clothes,
so all those husbands here
When you go home to your wife
and she sees something nice at the airport
[Music] it's
not allowed to say I'm Michael. He
told him
the expensive shawl is more than it uses up
seeds.
Don't tell your wife
that Michael already said she likes it, it's
cheap clothes. I did
n't say that,
I said
the husband who buys the best clothes for
his wife is a better seed,
what is
[Applause]
but it's like
those others
are burning a lot of seeds.
When you play a game of marbles
with other planets
you are using a lot of seeds
in that world,
but it seems one day it
's very, very, very expensive
karmatically.
What happens?
[Music]
So the great lamas say
your job in this life is
not to use seeds, it's to make
seeds.
Your job is not to have the most expensive car
or the biggest house or the most expensive shoes. You should
n't be a consumer of karma, you
should be a producer of karma.
[Music]
You have a choice in your life. You
can be the person who uses the most
seeds
or you can be the person who makes the most
seeds.
Our job is to make more seeds, not to
use more seeds. I
never said don't buy a Tesla,
no  I said that,
don't use more seeds than you can
sow
[Music]
fight a Tesla
but give a ride to many people
then you're making more
Tesla seeds than it cost you to buy it buy yourself nice
clothes pretty
clothes
take your friends to the cafe
teach them about the pen
100 points they'll be there watching you
are teaching the pen
if you're teaching it good
how good
today you look very good
very good
then you're making new seeds
you're making Buddha happy
so go ahead buy clothes quality
wear clothes gives when you teach this pen
but make more seeds than you're
using
how do you make more seeds than you're
[Music]
the seeds are mental
or I'm teaching my friend the pen
at the cafe
you have to tell your husband
sorry once I
have to teach the pen at the
cafe today
so in the morning it's okay I
buy myself a new dress then
later you say why is
n't it for me I'm
going to the cafe I have to teach the
pen
all the Buddhas to be there we
have to look good okay
if you do your motivation
which is true
if of  This motivation
will make you make many more seeds than you
used when you bought the dress. I
had millions of
smart purchases.
[Applause]
Someone told me, I alone this year in
Germany.
[Music]
Teach her level 10 of 16. I always
teach in Germany
for the first time because Silvia started
there, it says, in Germany,
and she published more of my books than
any other country.
Thanks
to level 10, not initial,
how not to get angry.
[Music]
They should come when we teach it in
China or Singapore,
and they should come.
Then many people ask me
what level
11 is. Always secretly,
what is level 11?
Sometimes, but don't tell other
people.
And advance purchases.
[Music]
How to go shopping,
how to go shopping, making more karma
than you're spending.
112.
If you buy a new shirt
[Music]
for the hunger class
and you're okay, how much did it cost?
How many seeds did I burn in these three
hours
to use? When using a new head,
I have to make more seeds than that.
How
then, if really,
the lord for three hours
Because I'm teaching the pen, the
Buddhas must come.
Because I'm protecting 500
people from going to hell,
the Buddhas have to come.
So I should wear a pretty blouse.
And if I think like that, I'm
going to make more good seeds than I
spend.
So I, Landano, said
never buy expensive clothes.
I just said
the seed you're spending, always make
more.
[Music]
What's the problem in that realm of
Buddhas?
They don't understand the pen. They
're just using the seeds.
All the debate dies. They go to hell
afterward
because they used all the good seeds
and didn't make new good seeds.
Let's stop for today.